<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<!doctype tei2 public "-//Library of Congress - Historical Collections (American Memory)//DTD ammem.dtd//EN" 
[<!entity % images system "n835o.ent"> %images;]>-->
<!--LINK TO  Votes for Women: Selections from the National American Woman Suffrage Association Collection, 1848-1921
http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/naw/nawshome.html <tei2>-->
<!-- Ortiz, Sandy INFO 246 Fall 2015 Final Project, 11/15/15-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
  <fileDesc>
     <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">
        The M.A.O.F.E.S.W [Massachusetts Association Opposed to the Further Extension of Suffrage to Woman] / by Alice Stone Blackwell:  a machine-readable
        transcription.
        </title>
        <author><orgName>National Digital Library Program, Library of Congress</orgName></author>
        <editor>Selected and converted.<lb/>
         American Memory, Library of Congress.<lb/>
        </editor>
     </titleStmt>
     <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>National Digital Library Program, Library of Congress</publisher>
        <idno type="aggitemid">rbnawsa-n835o</idno>
        <availability><p>Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p></availability>
     </publicationStmt>
     <notesStmt>
           <note>
            <p>Washington, DC, 1993.</p>
            <p>Preceding element provides place and date of transcription only.</p>
            <p>For more information about this text and this American Memory collection, refer to accompanying matter.</p>
           </note>
           <note>
            <p>Collection Name:</p>
            <p>Winning the Vote for Women:  The National American Woman Suffrage Association Collection; American Memory, Library of Congress.</p>
           </note>
      </notesStmt>
     <sourceDesc>
       <p>Selected from the National American Woman Suffrage Association Collection, Rare Book and Special Collections Division, Library of Congress.</p>
       <p>LCCN: None</p>
     </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc><p>The National Digital Library Program at the Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and
       scholarship.</p></projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl><p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy of 99.95 percent or greater and is not intended to reproduce the appearance 
       of the original work.  The accompanying images provide a facsimile of this work and represent the appearance of the original.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
     <language ident="en">English</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
     <change when="2003-08-19">Revised 08-01-2003</change>
     <change when="1995-09-28">Created 09-28-1995</change>
     <!--<encodingdate>1995/09/28</encodingdate>
     <revdate>2003/08/19</revdate>-->
  </revisionDesc>	
</teiHeader>
<text type="publication">
    <front>
       <!--<pageinfo>
       <controlpgno entity="n835o001">001</controlpgno>
       <printpgno></printpgno>
       </pageinfo>-->
       <pb n="01" facs="n835o001"/>
       <div type="idinfo">
         
          <p><stamp>492983</stamp></p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">Political Equality Series</hi><lb/>
          Vol. 2.  No. 4. <space quantity="20" unit="chars"/>Subscription Price, 10c Per Year
         
          </p>
         <lb/>
          <p>
            <stamp>
             <!--<omit reason="illegible">-->
             <del><gap reason="illegible"/></del>
            </stamp>
          </p>
          <p>Published monthly by the 
             <hi rend="smallcaps">
             National American<lb/>
             Woman Suffrage Association,
             </hi>
             Headquarters,<lb/>
             Warren, Ohio.
          </p>
        <lb/>
       </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
       <head>
       THE M. A. O. F. E. S. W.<lb/>
       By Alice Stone Blackwell
       </head>
       <p>
       The Massachusetts &#146; Association Opposed to the Further Extension of Suffrage to Women claims to have more than 12,000 members.  This statement gives a
       greatly exaggerated idea of its strength, if unaccompanied with an explanation as to what membership means.  In most societies, those who join pay a membership
       fee, and renew their membership from year to year.  The so-called members of the M.A.O.F.E.S.W. pay no membership fee; they merely sign an anti-suffrage
       document; and those who signed years ago are still counted as members today.  As Mrs. Mary A. Livermore pointed out, they show about the same amount of interest
       as the women who sign a suffrage petition.  Considering how easy it is to get people to sign almost anything, it is not at all remarkable that the
       &#147;Antis&#148; have been able in eleven years to collect 12,000 signatures.  In New York, at the time of the last constitutional convention, the suffragists
       secured more than 300,000 signatures in one year.  In Massachusetts, on the mock referendum taken in 1895, nearly twice as many women expressed themselves in
       favor of suffrage in one day as the &#147;Antis&#148; have induced to express themselves against it in eleven years 
       
       <!--<pageinfo>
       <controlpgno entity="n835o002">002</controlpgno>
       <printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
        <pb n="02" facs="n835o002"/>
        The M. A. O. F. E. S. W. lays great stress upon this so-called referendum, and sends out to all the other states documents giving
        a wholly misleading account of it.  The Oregon Association opposed to the Further Extension of Suffrage to Women in a recent pamphlet, based doubtless on
        information supplied by the Massachusetts &#147;Antis,&#148; said of this mock referendum, &#147;It had been clamored for most vigorously by the
        suffragists.&#148;  The Massachusetts suffragists had for nearly fifty years been asking the Legislature for a legal and valid referendum&#151;the submission to
        the voters of a constitutional amendment giving full suffrage to women.  The opponents in the Legislature always refused to submit it.  They also voted down a 
        bill to give women municipal suffrage, containing a proviso that the act should take effect only if ratified by a majority vote of both men and women at the 
        polls. Later, the Legislature asked the Supreme Court of Massachusetts whether municipal suffrage could legally be extended to women in this way.  The Supreme 
        Court ruled that the Legislature could not constitutionally pass an act making the extension of municipal suffrage to women contingent upon its ratification by
        a referendum vote, either of men alone or of men and women together.  The opponents in the Legislature refused to take such a referendum when they supposed it   
        would be constitutional, but no sooner did the Supreme Court declare that it would be unconstitutional than they became clamorous to have it.  They passed a bill
        to submit the question to a mock vote, which was to have no legal validity, and was to give the women nothing if the majority went in their
       <!--<pageinfo>
       <controlpgno entity="n835o003">003</controlpgno>
       <printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
        <pb n="03" facs="n835o003"/>
        favor.  The suffragists were so disgusted that many of them refused to take any part in it.  Nevertheless, the women&apos;s vote
        stood&#151;Yeas, 22,204; nays, 861.
       </p>
       <p>
       The &#147;Antis&#148; say that only four per cent. of the women of the state voted Yes.  They omit to say that less than one-sixth of one per cent. voted No. 
       They say there were 57 towns where not one woman voted for suffrage.  There were 47 towns where not one woman voted for suffrage; and there were 238 towns where
       not one woman voted against suffrage, despite the fact that an active &#147;Man Suffrage Association&#148; composed of prominent politicians covered the walls of
       every town in the state with large posters urging the women to vote no.
       </p>
       <p>
       The men&apos;s vote was in the negative, about two to one.  The men voting no were only 33 per cent. of the men of the state, but their verdict was considered
       decisive.
       </p>
       <p>
       The anti-suffrage politicians who had devised the scheme of the mock referendum regarded the women&apos;s vote as of little importance.  In a newspaper interview
       published shortly before the election, one of the officers of the &#147;Man Suffrage Association&#148; bluntly declared that the women who took the trouble to
       vote either way would probably vote in favor, ten to one (it proved to be 25 to one), but that, if the men gave a good majority against it, the Legislature coul be
       relied upon after that to vote it down.
       </p>
       <p>
       It is preposterous to quote the Massachusetts referendum as showing that the majority of women are opposed to suffrage.  Of the women who take any strong interest
       in the question either way, 
       <!--<pageinfo>
       <controlpgno entity="n835o004">004</controlpgno>
       <printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
        <pb n="04" facs="n835o004"/>
        the large majority are in favor.  This has been proved wherever the matter has been brought to a test.  In every state where
        petitions for suffrage and remonstrances against it have been sent in, the petitioners have always out-numbered the remonstrants, generally 50 or 100 to one. 
        The Massachusetts referendum merely demonstrated the same thing by an official count.
       </p>
    </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
           <p>
           <hi rend="italics">Send 10 cents to National Woman Suffrage<lb/>
           Headquarters, Warren, O., for a sample set of<lb/>
           the Political Equality Leaflets; also 25 cents for<lb/>
           a years subscription to Progress, the organ of<lb/>
           the National American Women Suffrage Association.</hi>
           </p>
           <p><hi rend="italics">
           For suffrage news, send 25 cents to the<lb/>
           Woman&apos;s Journal, 3 Park St, Boston, Mass., <lb/>
           edited weekly by Henry B. Blackwell and Alice <lb/>
           Stone Blackwell; 3 months on trial, 25 cents; one<lb/>
           year, $1.50.</hi>
           </p>
      </div>
    </back>
</text>
</TEI>