<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE TEI2 PUBLIC "-//Library of Congress - Historical Collections (American Memory)//DTD ammem.dtd//EN" 
[<!entity % images system "n8346.ent"> %images;]><tei2>
LINK TO  Votes for Women: Selections from the National American Woman Suffrage Association Collection, 1848-1921
http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/naw/nawshome.html-->
<!-- Ortiz, Sandy INFO 246 Fall 2015 Final Project, 12/05/15-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title type="main"> Bible and church degrade woman/by Elizabeth Cady Stanton</title>
			<author><orgName>National Digital Library Program, Library of Congress</orgName></author>
			<editor>Selected and converted.<lb/>
					American Memory, Library of Congress.<lb/>
			</editor>
			
			<respStmt>
				<resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
				<orgName>American Memory, Library of Congress.</orgName>
			</respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
			<publisher>National Digital Library Program, Library of Congress</publisher>
			<idno type="lccn">93-838346</idno>
			<idno type="aggitemid">rbnawsa-n8346</idno>
			<availability><p>Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p></availability>
		</publicationStmt>
	 	<notesStmt>
	 		<note>
	 		<p>Washington, DC, 1993.</p>
			<p>Preceding element provides place and date of transcription only. </p>
			<p>For more information about this text and this American Memory collection, refer to accompanying matter. </p>
	 		</note>
	 	</notesStmt>
	 	<sourceDesc>
	 		<p>Selected from the National American Woman Suffrage Association Collection, Rare Book and Special Collections Division, Library of Congress.</p>
	 		<p>LCCN: 93-838346</p>
	 	</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
	   <projectDesc><p>The National Digital Library Program at the Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and scholarship.</p></projectDesc>
	   <editorialDecl><p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy of 99.95 percent or greater and is not intended to reproduce the appearance of the original work.  The accompanying images provide a facsimile of this work and represent the appearance of the original.</p></editorialDecl>
	   
	</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<creation>
			<date when="1895">[1898?]</date>
			<rs type="city">Chicago,Ill</rs>
		</creation>
		<langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
		</langUsage>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change when="2003-08-19">Revised 08-1-2003</change>
		<change when="1995-10-27">Created 10-27-1995</change>
		<!--<encodingdate>1995/10/27</encodingdate>
	   <revdate>2003/08/19</revdate>-->	
	</revisionDesc>	
</teiHeader>
<text type="publication">
	<front>
		<!--Replace all <pageinfo> with <pb> to be TEI Level 4 compliant-->
		<pb n="0a" facs="8346001.bmp">
		<!--<pageinfo><controlpgno entity="n8346001">001</controlpgno>
		<printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
		</pb>
		<div>
			<div>
				<p>
				LIBRARY
				<lb/>
				CARRIE CHAPMAN CATT
				<lb/>
				SUBJECT 
				<!--<handwritten>-->
				SECTION V
				<lb/>
				Woman - Sociology &amp; Ethics
				<!--</handwritten>-->
				<lb/>
				NO. 
				<!--<handwritten>-->
				25
				<!--</handwritten>-->
				</p>
			</div>

			<pb n="0b" facs="8346002.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346002">002</controlpgno>
			<printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			<!--<p>-->
			<!--<handwritten>-->
			<div>
			<p>
			Mrs. Carrie Chapman Catt
			<lb/>
			Compliments of
			<lb/>
			Elizabeth Cady Stanton
			<lb/>
			Born at Johnstown - Lutton Co. New York
			<lb/>
			November 12th 1815
			<lb/>
			April 24th 1901
			<lb/>
			250 West 94th St. New York.
			<!--</handwritten>-->
			</p>
			</div>
		</div>
		<pb n="0c" facs="8346003.bmp">
		<!--<pageinfo>
		<controlpgno entity="n8346003">003</controlpgno>
		<printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
		</pb>
		<div type="idinfo">
			<p>
			Price, 10 Cents
				<lb/>
				Twelve Copies for $1.00
				<lb/>
				Bible and Church Degrade
				<lb/>
				WOMAN
			</p>
			<p>
			CONTENTS
			</p>
			<div>
				<p>
				Page
				</p>
				<p>
				I.  The Effect of Woman Suffrage on Questions of Morals and Religion, 
				<space quantity="5" unit="chars"/>
				1
				</p>
				<p>
				II.  The Degraded Status of Woman in the Bible,
				<space quantity="5" unit="chars"/>
				5
				</p>
				<p>
				III.  The Christian Church and Woman,
				<space quantity="5" unit="chars"/>
				11
				</p>
			</div>
			<div>
			<p>
			BY
			<lb/>
			ELIZABETH CADY STANTON
			</p>
			<p>
			H. L. GREEN, Publisher
			<lb/>
			Office of Free Thought Magazine, 213 East Indiana Street
			<lb/>
			CHICAGO, ILL.
			</p>
			</div>
			<pb n="0d" facs="8346004.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346004">004</controlpgno>
			<printpgno></printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			
			<div>
				<p>Sincerely yours
				<lb/>
				Elizabeth Cady Stanton
				<lb/>
				</p>
			</div>
		</div>
	</front>
	<body>
		<pb n="1" facs="8346005.bmp">
		<!--<pageinfo>
		  <controlpgno entity="n8346005">005</controlpgno>
		  <printpgno>1</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
		</pb>
		<div>
			<head>
			THE EFFECT OF WOMAN SUFFRAGE ON QUESTIONS OF   
			<lb/>  
			MORALS AND RELIGION. 
			<lb/>
			BY ELIZABETH CADY STANTON.
			</head>
			  <p>
				<!--<hi rend="other"> Lecky	</hi>-->
				Lecky, in his late work on Democracy, expresses the opinion that the emotional nature of woman, her religious enthusiasm, would make her influence dangerous in public legislation where calm, clear in judgment is needed.  He quotes as illustration, the opposition of English women to vivisection, under all circumstances, even in the hands of humane, honorable physicians.  They insisted that no benefit could come to the human family from such experiments, in direct opposition to the opinions of distinguished surgeons in Germany and France. </p>
			  <p>
			  When last in England my daughter and I spent an hour with Frances Power Cobbe, the chief leader against vivisection.  Her office was filled with books and pictures illustrating the cruelties of the experiments, enough to fill the hardest nature with pity and revulsion at the whole system.  While sympathizing with Miss Cobbe&apos;s views, and sincerely deploring all cruelties to animals, we could not believe that all physicians were conducting their experiments for their own amusement. </p>
			  <p>
			  At the close of the interview Miss Cobbe, turning to my daughter, said, &#147;After all I have shown you here to-day, would you shake hands with a vivisectionist?&#148; </p>
			  <p>
			  &#147;Yes,&#148; she replied, &#147;I was proud to shake hands with the great German scientist Virchow, because he respected the ambition of a 
			  <pb n="2" facs="8346006.bmp" break="yes">
			  <!--<pageinfo>
			  <controlpgno entity="n8346006">006</controlpgno>
			  <printpgno>2</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>young New England girl; when all the other professors refused to admit her to their classes, he welcomed her to his lectures, required his students to treat her with courtesy, and taught her all she desired to know. </p>
			  <p>
			  &#147;Would you refuse to shake hands with college professors who would recklessly trample on the pride and hopes of earnest young girls?&#148; </p>
			  <p>
			  Miss Cobbe hesitated a moment and said, &#147;Perhaps not.&#148;  &#147;The difference between us, then,&#148; my daughter replied, &#147;is that you appreciate the physical sufferings of the dog, while I comprehend the keener mental sufferings of the girl.&#148;  &#147;Ah, yes,&#148; &#147;if there were some instrument in the world of sorrows to measure the sufferings of women&#151;their development rudely arrested, hopes disappointed, pride humbled, ambition crushed, aspirations perverted, crippled with fears on every side&#151;woman&apos;s wrongs in a single generation would outweigh the sufferings of animal life for centuries.  The torture of nerves and muscles is limited, compared with prolonged or oft repeated mental agonies during four score years and ten.&#148; </p>
			  <p>
			  Lecky might further have illustrated the dangerous influence of English women in public affairs, by their persecution of Charles Parnell, M.P.  They took the untenable position, that if man&apos;s social relations were not in harmony with English law, he could not be a statesman to be trusted with great public interests.  He was the only man who had been able to keep the Home Rule question steadily before Parliament, yet they hounded him to his grave, killed that great measure and left poor Ireland to struggle in her chains another generation. </p>
			  <p>
			  If about to start on a dangerous voyage, one would naturally ask if the captain had skill and experience in the science of navigation, but no one would think of asking whether in social life he was governed by the moral code of England or Japan. </p>
			  <p>
			  Many of the most liberal men in this country who believe in self-government for women, fear, with Mr. Lecky, the effect of woman&apos;s religious bigotry on the secular nature of our government. </p>
			  <p>
			  The action of women in some cases has given ground for these opinions.  To hold the mirror up to women, that they may see themselves 
			  <pb n="3" facs="8346007.bmp">
			  <!--<pageinfo>
			  <controlpgno entity="n8346007">007</controlpgno>
			  <printpgno>3</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>as others see them, I will give a few cases.  To push what they consider a moral measure, they have sometimes acted in violation of law.  In the early temperance crusade in Ohio, they walked into the drinking saloons, smashed the bottles right and left, emptied the liquor into the street, and then with hymns and prayers endeavored to impress their victims with the sacredness of their proceedings.  But this was not law, though sanctified with religious enthusiasm. </p>
			  <p>
			  Such measures coined into law, by responsible voters, would soon lead to revolution. </p>
			  <p>
			  We had another manifestation of this dangerous enthusiasm, in the attempt to close the Chicago Exposition on Sunday.  Led by the Temperance Association, 100,000 persons, chiefly women, petitioned Congress to make no appropriation to the Exposition unless the managers pledged themselves to close it on Sunday, the only day in the week the masses could enjoy it.  What an outrage it would have been to close that magnificent spectacle, and drive the multitudes back into the crowded streets of the city!  Yet this was the verdict of 100,000 petitioners, chiefly women. </p>
			  <p>
			  I immediately published a leaflet in favor of opening the Exposition on Sunday, and sent it broadcast over the country.  Five hundred of these leaflets, by chance, fell into the hands of one of these religious bigots, which she promptly threw into the fire. </p>
			  <p>
			  I was surprised that she dared thus to trespass upon my friendship, but I simply said in a letter, &#147;In tampering with my mail you are guilty of a state&apos;s prison offense, but I will not incarcerate you; I simply suggest in passing, that if you had lived in the time of Calvin, you would as readily have burned me, and thought you did God service.&#148; </p>
			  <p>
			  There is no doubt that in their present religious bondage, the political influence of women would be against the secular nature of our government, so carefully guarded by the fathers.  They would, if possible, restore the Puritan Sabbath and sumptuary laws, and have the name of God and the Christian religion recognized in the National Constitution, thus granting privileges to one set over another, involving no end of religious persecutions. </p>
			  <p>
			  Admit all the danger herein set forth, shall we deny the right of 
			  <pb n="4" facs="8346008.bmp">
			  <!--<pageinfo>
			  <controlpgno entity="n8346008">008</controlpgno>
			  <printpgno>4</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>self-government to women, because through ignorance they may at first abuse their power?  No, no; these dangerous influences are steadily at work, reflected in every cradle, to be traced in every blind, conservative, bigoted priest, unjust judge, and wily statesman, the more dangerous because unrecognized and irresponsible. </p>
			  <p>
			  Woman&apos;s education has been left too much to the church, which has made her a devotee, training her sentiments and emotions at the expense of her reason and common sense.  The state must now open to her a wider field of though and action. </p>
			  <p>
			  We must turn the tide of her enthusiasm from the church to the state, arouse her patriotism; awaken her interest in great public questions, on which depend the stability of the republic and the elevation of the race, instead of wasting so much time and thought on the salvation of her own soul.  In her education hereafter substitute reason for blind faith, science for theological superstitions; then will our most liberal men, our scientists, scholars and statesmen, find in the women of their households a reserve force for building a higher, purer civilization. </p>
		</div>
		
		
		<div>
			<pb n="5" facs="8346009.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
		  <controlpgno entity="n8346009">009</controlpgno>
		  <printpgno>5</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>	
			  <head>
			  THE DEGRADED STATUS OF WOMAN IN THE BIBLE.
			  <lb/>
			  BY ELIZABETH CADY STANTON.
			  </head>
			   
			  <p>
			  <!--<hi rend="other"> The</hi>-->
			   The Pentateuch makes woman a mere afterthought in creation; the author of sin; cursed in her maternity; a subject in marriage; and claims divine authority for this fourfold bondage, this wholesale desecration of the mothers of the race.  While some admit that this invidious language of the Old Testament is disparaging to woman, they claim that the New testament honors her.  But the letters of the apostles to the churches, giving directions for the discipline of women, are equally invidious, as the following texts prove: </p>
			  <p>
			  &#147;Wives, obey your husbands.  If you would know anything, ask your husbands at home.  Let your women keep silence in the churches, with their heads covered.  Let not your women usurp authority over the man, for as Christ is the head of the church so is the man the head of the woman.  Man was prior in creation, the woman was of the man, therefore shall be in subjection to him.&#148; 
			  </p>
			  <p>
			  No symbols or metaphors can twist honor or dignity out of such sentiments.  Here, in plain English, woman&apos;s position is as
			  degrade as in the Old Testament. </p>
			  <p>
			  As the Bible is in every woman&apos;s hands, and she is trained to believe it &#147;the word of God,&#148; it is impossible to describe her 
			  feelings of doubt and distrust, as she awakes to her status in the scale of being; the helpless, hopeless position assigned her by the Creator, 
			  according to the Scriptures. </p>
			  <p>
			  Men can never understand the fear of everlasting punishment that fills the souls of women and children.  The orthodox religion, as 
			  <pb n="6" facs="8346010.bmp">
			  <!--<pageinfo>
			  <controlpgno entity="n8346010">010</controlpgno>
			  <printpgno>6</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>drawn from the Bible and expounded by the church, is enough to drive the most imaginative and sensitive natures to despair and death.  Having conversed with many young women in sanatoriums, insane asylums, and in the ordinary walks of life, suffering with religions melancholia; having witnessed the agony of young mothers in childbirth, believing they were cursed of God in their maternity; and with painful memories of my own fears and bewilderment in girlhood, I have endeavored to dissipate these religious superstitions from the minds of women, and base their faith on science and reason, where I found for myself at last that peace and comfort I could never find in the Bible and the church.  I saw the first step to this end was to convince them that the Bible was neither written nor inspired by the Creator of the Universe, the Infinite Intelligence, the soul and center of Life, Love and Light; but that the Bible emanated, in common with all church literature, from the brain of man.  Seeing that just in proportion as women are devout believers in the dogmas of the church their lives are shadowed with fears of the unknown, the less they believe, the better for their own happiness and development.  It was the religious devotee that threw her child under the car of Juggernaut, that gave her body a living sacrifice on the funeral pyre of her husband, to please God and save souls; for the same reason the devotees of our day build churches and parsonages, educate young men for the ministry, endow theological seminaries, make surplices and embroider slippers for the priesthood. </p>
			  <p>
			  It may not be amiss for man to accept the Bible, as it honors and exalts him.  It is a title deed for him to inherit the earth.  According to the Pentateuch he communes with the gods, in performing miracles he is equal in power and glory with his Creator, can command the sun and moon to stand still to lengthen the day and lighten the night, if need be, to finish his battles.  He can stand in the most holy places in the temples, where woman may never enter; he can eat the consecrated bread and meat, denied her; in fact, there is a suspicion of unworthiness and uncleanness seductively infused into the books of Moses against the whole female sex, in animal as well as human life.   
			  <!--<hi rend="italics"> The first born male</hi>-->
			  	The first born male kid is the only fit burnt offering to the Lord; of preceded by a female it is unfit. </p>
			  <pb n="7" facs="8346011.bmp">
				  <!--<pageinfo>
				  <controlpgno entity="n8346011">011</controlpgno>
				  <printpgno>7</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>
			  <p>
			  As the Bible gives us two opposite accounts of the creation of woman and her true position, so the church gives two opposite interpretations of the will of the God concerning her true sphere of action.  When ecclesiastics wish to rouse woman&apos;s enthusiasm to lift a church debt or raise a pastor&apos;s salary, then they try to show her that she owes all she is and all the liberty she enjoys to the Bible and Christian religion; they dwell on the great honor God conferred on the sex in choosing a woman to be the mother of his only begotten son. </p>
			  <p>
			  But when woman asks for equal rights and privileges in the church, to fill the office of pastor, elder, deacon or trustee, to be admitted as a delegate to the synods, general assemblies or conferences, then the bishops quote texts to show that all these positions are forbidden by the Bible.  And so completely have these clerical tergiversations perverted the religious element in woman&apos;s nature, and blinded her to her individual interests, that she does not see that her religious bondage is the source of her degradation. </p>
			  <p>
			  The honor and worship accorded the ideal mother, of the ideal man, has done naught to elevate the real mother, of the real man.  So far from woman owing what liberty she does enjoy, to the Bible and the church, they have been the greatest block in the way of her development.  The vantage ground woman holds to-day is due to all the forces of civilization, to science, discovery, invention, rationalism, the religion of humanity chanted in the golden rule round the globe centuries before the Christian religion was known.  It is not to Bibles, prayer books, catechisms, liturgies, the canon law and church creeds and organizations, that woman owes one step in her progress, for all these alike have been hostile, and still are, to her freedom and development. </p>
			  <p>
			  Canon Charles Kingsley well said, long ago:  &#147;This will never be a good world for woman, until the last remnant of the canon law is swept from the face of the earth.&#148;  It is the insidious influence of this law that degrades woman to-day in social life and the state as well as in the church; giving us one moral code for man, another for woman, endowing him with political freedom, with all the rights that belong to a citizen of a republic, while she is a slave, a subject, a mere pariah in the state. </p>
			  <pb n="8" facs="8346012.bmp">
				  <!--<pageinfo>
				  <controlpgno entity="n8346012">012</controlpgno>
				  <printpgno>8</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>
			  <p>
			  When the canon law with its joy fingers touched the old Roman civil law it robbed woman of many privileges she before enjoyed.  The old English common law, too, reflects many of its hideous features and has infused its deadly poison into the statute laws of every state in this new republic.  For fifty years the women of this nation have tried to dam up this deadly stream that poisons all their lives, but thus far they have lacked the insight or courage to follow it back to its source and there strike the blow at the fountain of all tyranny, religious superstition, priestly power and the canon law.  We may learn the effect of the canon on the civil law from the opinion of Lord Brougham.  He says the English common law for woman is a disgrace to the civilization and Christianity of the nineteenth century.  When last in England, hearing that the vicar had numberless volumes of the canon law, I called on him and asked to see the volume that contained the laws for women.  &#147;Ah!&#148; said he, &#147;they run through the whole of them,&#148; pointing to a long row of huge volumes bound in heavy calf and tightly clasped, &#147;and they are all in Latin.&#148;  I thought I could muster the patience and enough of my former knowledge of Latin for one volume, but not for a prolonged search through so many.  However, a learned and liberal scholar told me afterwards that we have the essence of the canon law in the Scriptures, in the creeds, dogmas and literature of the church, in plain English that any ordinary mind can understand.  The simple story of the Scotch peasant&apos;s wife shows how the Book impresses a thoughtful woman, not blinded by fear, to express her real opinions. </p>
			  <p>
			  Sitting in her cottage door at the twilight hour reading her Bible, the bishop passing by, said, &#147;My good woman, do you enjoy that book?&#148; &#147;Nay, nay, Reverend Sir, as I read of all the misery woman brought into the world, and for which there is no remedy, I am ashamed that I was born a woman.  I am sorry that the good Lord ever wrote the Book, and told the men all he has concerning us; it gives them an excuse for the contempt and cruelty with which they treat us.&#148;  Yea, verily, here is the source and center of woman&apos;s degradation; out of these ideas grew witchcraft and celibacy, that made woman for ages the helpless victim of man&apos;s lust and power; out of these ideas grew the monstrous delusion of the curse and uncleanness 
			  <pb n="9" facs="8346013.bmp">
				  <!--<pageinfo>
				  <controlpgno entity="n8346013">013</controlpgno>
				  <printpgno>9</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>
			  of motherhood, that required all women at one time to stand up before the whole congregation &#147;to be churched&#148; as it was called, after the birth of a child, returning thanks to the Lord for her safety.  As if peril and suffering were part of the eternal law, and not the result of its violation through our own ignorance and folly, and our artificial habits of life.  However, there are some considerations and characters in the Book that can give woman a few crumbs of comfort.  The first chapter of Genesis has several valuable suggestions.  &#147;God said, Let us make man in our own image.  Male and female made he   them, and gave them 
			 <!-- <hi rend="italics">them,</hi>  and gave <hi rend="italics">them</hi>-->
			   dominion over the earth, and all that dwells therein.&#148;  &#147;Let us,&#148; shows plurality in the Godhead, a heavenly mother as well as a heavenly father, the feminine as well as the masculine element.  Without these two forces in equilibrium, there could have been no perpetuation of life in the mineral, vegetable and animal kingdoms; as necessary in the material world as the positive and negative electricity, the centripetal and centrifugal forces.  &#147;He gave them dominion over everything.&#148;  Here the equality of the sexes is recognized, and this idea is echoed back from the New Testament.  &#147;There is neither Jew nor Greek, male nor female, bond nor free, for ye are all one in Christ Jesus.&#148;  We not only have this broad principle of equality enunciated, but we have some grand types of women presented for our admiration.  Deborah for her courage and military prowess.  Huldah for her learning, prophetic insight, and statesmanship, seated in the college in Jerusalem, where Josiah the king sends his cabinet ministers to consult her as to the policy of his government.  Esther, who ruled as well as reigned with Ahasuerus the king, and Vashti, who scorned the apostle&apos;s command, &#147;Wives, obey your husbands.&#148;  She refused the king&apos;s command to grace with her presence his reveling court.  Tennyson pays this tribute to her virtue and dignity: 
			  <lb/>
			  <hi rend="blockindent">&#147;O Vashti!  noble Vashti, <lb/>
			  Summoned forth, she kept her state  <lb/>
			  And left the drunken king to brawl  <lb/>
			  In Shushan underneath his palms.&#148;</hi>
			  </p>
			  <p>
			  These characters and principles would furnish good texts for sermons and examples for aspiring young women in the churches, but the sons of Levi shy round all these interesting facts, and maintain 
			  <pb n="10" facs="8346014.bmp">
			  <!--<pageinfo>
			  <controlpgno entity="n8346014">014</controlpgno>
			  <printpgno>10</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			  </pb>
			  a discreet silence, but they should awake woman to her true position as an equal factor in the scale of being.  We never have any sermons to inspire woman with self-respect and a desire for her own higher development.  The cardinal virtue for her to cultivate is self-sacrifice and an humble submission to the discipline of the church.  As a badge of her subjection she is always required to appear in church with her head covered. </p>
			  <p>
			  When last in Europe the wife of an English officer told me that she tried the experiment of going to church without her bonnet one warm day in summer.  As she walked up the center aisle with her husband every neck was craned to see the unusual sight and it caused such a flutter in the congregation, and such severe strictures by the saints, that the vicar called in the course of the week to request that the experiment should not be repeated.  However, she found it so comfortable to sit with her head bare during the long service, and as her husband sustained her, she continued to go with her head uncovered on several occasions.  Then the bishop wrote her a letter, saying that the discipline of the church required every woman to attend service with her head covered, and that unless she was willing to comply with the long established religious custom, significant of woman&apos;s true position as set forth in the Scriptures, she must not enter the cathedral again. </p>
			  <p>
			  At a lunch party one day in London, the lady read the bishop&apos;s letter, to the great amusement of those present.  All joined in the hope that many other women would follow this worthy example.  If a bonnet is a badge of subjection, it should be thrown to the winds without further delay.  As women are now required to doff their bonnets in operas and theaters, why cling to this badge of servitude in the churches? </p>
		</div>
			<pb n="11" facs="8346015.bmp">
		<!--<pageinfo>
		<controlpgno entity="n8346015">015</controlpgno>
		<printpgno>11</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
		</pb>
		<div>
			<head>
			THE CHRISTIAN CHURCH AND WOMAN.
			<lb/>
			BY ELIZABETH CADY STANTON.
			</head>
			<p>
			<!--<hi rend="other">THE</hi>-->
			 THE grand ideas of Confucius, Zorcaster, Buddha, Mohammed, Jesus, have been slowly transforming the world from the reign of brute force to moral power, and science has been as slowly emancipating mankind from their fears of the unknown; but the Christian Church has steadily used its influence against progress, science, the education of the masses and freedom for woman.  It is often asserted that woman owes all the advantages of the position she occupies to-day to Christianity, but the facts of history show that the Christian Church has done nothing specifically for woman&apos;s elevation.  In the general march of civilization she has necessarily reaped the advantage of man&apos;s higher development; but we must not claim for Christianity all that has been achieved by science, discovery and invention. </p>
			<p>
			If we admit that the truth it has taught, as an offset to its many errors, has been one of the factors in civilization, we shall concede all that can be fairly claimed.  The prolonged slavery of woman is the darkest page in human history; and she has touched the depths of misery since in Bethlehem the Magi gathered round the child in the manger, who was hailed as the Savior of mankind.  But the life and teachings of Jesus, all pointing to the complete equality of the human family, were too far in advance of his age to mould its public opinion.  We must distinguish between the teachings attributed to Jesus and those of the Christian Church.  One represents the ideal the race in destined to attain; the other, the popular sentiment of its time. </p>
			<p>
			Had Jesus lived in Russia in the nineteenth century, he would have been exiled as a Nihilist for his protests against tyranny and his sympathy with the suffering masses.  He would have been driven from Germany as a socialist, from France as a communist, and imprisoned as a blasphemer in England and America, had he taught in London and New York the radical ideas be proclaimed in Palestine. </p>
			<pb n="12" facs="8346016.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346016">016</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>12</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			<p>
			I speak of the Christian Church, Catholic and Protestant, of the priesthood, the bulls of its popes, the decrees of its councils, the articles and resolutions of its general assemblies, presbyteries, synods, conferences, which, all summed up, compose the canon law, which has held Christendom during what are called the Dark Ages until now under its paralyzing influence, moulding civil law and social customs and plunging woman into absolute slavery. </p>
			<p>
			The worst features of the canon law reveal themselves to-day in woman&apos;s condition as clearly as they did fifteen hundred years ago.  The clergy in their pulpits, teach the same doctrines in regard to her from the same texts, and echo the same old platitudes and false ideas promulgated for centuries by ecclesiastical councils.  According to Church teaching, woman was an after-thought in the creation, the author of sin, being at once in collusion with Satan.  Her sex was made a crime; marriage a condition of slavery, owing obedience; maternity a curse; and the true position of all womankind one of inferiority and subjection to all men; and the same ideas are echoed in our pulpits to-day. </p>
			<p>
			England and America are the two nations in which the Christian religion is dominant; yet, by their ethics taught in the pulpit, the ideal woman is comparatively more degraded than in pagan nations.  I say comparatively, for, because of the various steps of progress in education, science, invention and art, woman is now more fully the equal of man in these countries than in any other nation or period of the world.  And yet the old ideas taught by the Church in the Dark Ages of her inferiority and depravity are still maintained; and, just in proportion as women are the equals of men by their side, the more keenly they feel every invidious distinction based on sex.  To those not conversant with the history of the Christian Church and the growth of the canon law, it may seem a startling assertion; but it is, nevertheless, true that the Church has done more to degrade woman than all other adverse influences put together.  And it has done this by playing on the religious emotions (the strongest feelings of her nature) to her own complete subjugation.  The same religious conscience that carried the widows to the funeral pyre of their husbands now holds some women in the Turkish seraglios, others in 
			<pb n="13" facs="8346017.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346017">017</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>13</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			polygamy under the Mormon theocracy, and others in the Christian churches, in which, while rich women help to build and support them, they may not speak or vote or enjoy any of the honors conferred on men, and all alike are taught that their degradation is of divine ordination, and thus their natural feelings of self-respect are held in abeyance to what they are taught to believe is God&apos;s will.  Out of the doctrine of original sin grew the crimes and miseries of asceticism, celibacy, and witchcraft, woman becoming the helpless victim of all the delusions generated in the brain of man. </p>
			<p>
			Having decided that she was the author of sin and the medium through whom the devil would effect the downfall of the Church, godly men logically inferred that the greater the distance between themselves and all womankind, the nearer they were to God and heaven.  With this idea, they fought against all woman&apos;s influence, both good and evil.  At one period, they crucified all natural affections for mother, sister, wife and daughter, and continued a series of persecutions that blackened the centuries with the most horrible crimes. </p>
			<p>
			This more than any other one influence was the cause of that general halt in civilization, that retrogressive movement of the Dark Ages, for which no historian has satisfactorily accounted.  At no period of the world was the equilibrium of the masculine and feminine elements of humanity so disturbed.  The result was moral chaos&#151;just what would occur in the material world, if it were possible to destroy the equilibrium of the positive and negative electricity or of the centripetal and centrifugal force. </p>
			<p>
			For the supposed crimes of heresy and witchcraft hundreds of women endured such persecutions and tortures that the most stolid historians are said to have wept in recording them; and no one can read them to-day but with a bleeding heart.  And, as the Christian Church grew stronger, woman&apos;s fate grew more helpless.  Even the Reformation and Protestantism brought no relief, the clergy being all along their most bitter persecutors, the inventors of the most infernal tortures.  Hundreds and hundreds of fair young girls, innocent as the angels in heaven, hundreds and hundreds of old women, weary and trembling with the burdens of life, were hunted down by emissaries of the Church, dragged into the courts, with the ablest 
			<pb n="14" facs="8346018.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346018">018</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>14</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>judges and lawyers of England, Scotland and America on the bench, and tried for crimes that never existed but in the wild, fanatical imaginations of religious devotees.  Women were acused of consorting with devils and perpetuating their diabolical propensities.  Hundreds of these children of hypothetical origin were drowned, burned and tortured in the presence of their mothers, to add to their death agonies.  These things were not done by savages or pagans; they were done by the Christian Church.  Neither were they confined to the Dark Ages, but permitted by law in England far into the eighteenth century.  The clergy everywhere sustained witchcraft as Bible doctrine, until the spirit of rationalism laughed the whole thing to scorn, and science gave mankind a more cheerful view of life. </p>
			<p>
			So large a place has the nature and position of woman occupied in the councils of the Church that the Rev. Charles Kingsley facetiously remarked that the Christian Church was swamped by hysteria from the third to the sixteenth century.  Speaking of witchcraft, Lecky says the Reformation was the signal for a fresh outburst of the superstition in England; and there, as elsewhere, its decline was represented by the clergy as the direct consequence and the exact measure of the progress of religious skepticism.  In Scotland, where the reformed ministers exercised greater influence than in any other country, and where the witch trials fell almost entirely into their hands, the persecution was proportionally atrocious.  Probably the ablest defender of the belief was Glanvil, a clergyman of the English Establishment; and one of the most influential was Baxter, the greatest of the Puritans.  It spread with Puritanism into the New World, and the executions in Massachusetts form one of the darkest pages in American history.  The greatest religious leader of the last century, John Wesley, was among the latest of its supporters.  He said giving up witchcraft was giving up the Bible.  Skepticism on the subject of witches first arose among those who were least governed by the Church, advanced with the decline of the influence of the clergy, and was commonly branded by them as a phase of infidelity. </p>
			<p>
			One remarkable fact stands out in the history of witchcraft; and that is, its victims were chiefly women.  Scarce one wizard to a hundred witches was ever burned or tortured. </p>
			<pb n="15" facs="8346019.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346019">019</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>15</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			<p>
			Although the ignorance and crimes of the race have ever fallen most heavily on woman, yet in the general progress of civilization she has had some share.  As man became more enlightened, she of necessity enjoyed the results; but to no form of popular religion has woman ever been indebted for one pulsation of liberty.  Obedience and subjection have been the lessons taught her by all alike. </p>
			<p>
			Lecky, in his History of Rationalism and his European Morals, gives facts sufficient to convince any woman of common sense that the greatest obstacle in the way of the freedom and elevation of her sex has been, and is, the teaching of the Church in regard to her rights and duties.  Women have ever been the chief victims in the persecutions of the Church amid all its awful tragedies, and on them have fallen the heaviest penalties of the canon law. </p>
			<p>
			But the canon law did not confine itself to social relations; it laid its hand with withering touch on the civil law, and blighted many personal and property rights accorded woman under the Roman Code. </p>
			<p>
			Speaking of the Roman Code before the introduction of Christianity (Gaius), Maine says:  &#147;The jurisconsults had evidently at this time assumed the equality of the sexes as a principle to the code of equity.  The situation of the Roman woman, whether married or single, became one of the great personal and property independence, but Christianity tended somewhat from the very first to narrow this remarkable liberty.  The prevailing state of religious sentiment may explain why modern jurisprudence has adopted these rules concerning the position of woman, which belong peculiarly to an imperfect civilization.  No society which preserves any tincture of Christian institutions is likely to restore to married women the personal liberty conferred on them by middle Roman law.  Canon law has deeply injured civilization.&#148; </p>
			<p>
			Rev. Charles Kingsley says:  &#147;Whoever wishes to gain insight into that great institution, Canon Law, can do so most effectively by studying Common Law in regard to woman.  There will never be a good world for woman until the last remnant of Canon Law is civilized off the face of the earth.  Meanwhile, all the most pure and high-minded women in England and Europe have been brought up under the shadow of the Canon Law, and have accepted it, with the 
			<pb n="16" facs="8346020.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346020">020</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>16</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			usual divine self-sacrifice, as their destiny by law of God and nature, and consider their own womanhood outraged, when it, their tyrant, is meddled with.&#148;  Woman accept their position under the shadow of the canon law for the best of reasons&#151;they know nothing about it.  And, if they should undertake to explore it, they would waste their lives in the effort. </p>
			<p>
			This is one of the peculiarities of woman&apos;s position; she knows nothing of the laws, either canon or civil, under which she lives; and such churchmen as the Rev. Morgan Dix are determined she never shall.  Nero was thought the chief of tyrants because he made laws and hung them up so high the people could not read them. </p>
			<p>
			As the result of the canon law, what is woman&apos;s position in the State and the Church to-day?  We have woman disfranchised, with no voice in the government under which she lives, denied until recently the right to enter colleges or professions, laboring at half-price in the world of work; a code of morals that makes man&apos;s glory woman&apos;s shame; a civil code that makes her in marriage a nonentity, her person, her children, her earnings the property of her husband.  In adjusting this institution of marriage, woman has never yet in the history of the word to say.  The relation has been absolutely established and perpetuated without her consent.  We have thus far had the man marriage.  He has made all the laws concerning it to suit his own convenience and love of power.  He has tried every possible form of it, and is as yet satisfied with none of his experiments.  If an inhabitant of some other planet could suddenly light in one of our law libraries, and read over our civil and criminal codes, he would be at loss to know what kind of beings women are, so anomalous is the position we hold, with some rights partially recognized in one place and wholly obliterated in another.  In the criminal code, we find no feminine pronouns.  All criminals are designated as &#147;he,&#148; &#147;his,&#148; &#147;him.&#148;  We might suppose our fathers thought women were too pure and angelic ever to commit crimes, if we did not find in the law reports, cases in which women had been imprisoned and hung as &#147;he,&#148; &#147;his,&#148; &#147;him.&#148;  And yet, when it comes to privileges we are excluded, because the laws and constitutions do not contain the feminine pronouns &#147;she,&#148; &#147;hers,&#148; &#147;her.&#148;  We are kind of half human, half animal being, 
			<pb n="17" facs="8346021.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346021">021</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>17</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			like those wonderful questioning sphinxes we see in the Old World. </p>
			<p>
			And we present very much the same appearance in the Church.  Go into any little country town, and the chief excitement among the women is found in fairs, donation parties, festivals, church building and decorating.  The women are the chief, untiring, pertinacious beggars for the church.  They compose the vast majority of the congregation.  Rich women give large sums to clear church debts, to educate young men for the ministry, and to endow theological seminaries.  Poorer women decorate the temples for Christmas and Easter, make surplices and gowns, embroider table covers for the altar, and slippers for the rector; and all alike think they are serving God in sustaining the Church and the priesthood. </p>
			<p>
			In return, the whole tone of Church teaching in regard to woman is, to the last degree, contemptuous and degrading. </p>
			<p>
			Perchance the very man educated by some sewing society of women will ascend the pulpit, and take his test in 1 Corinthians xiv. 34, 35:  &#147;Let your women keep silence in the churches; for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but they are commanded to be under obedience, as also saith the law.  And if they will learn anything, let them ask their husbands at home, for it is a shame for women to speak in the church.&#148;  Ephesians v. 23:  &#147;Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord.  For the husband is the head of the wife, even as Christ is the head of the Church.&#148;  1 Timothy ii. 11, 12, 13:  &#147;Let the women learn in silence with all subjection.  But I suffer not a woman to teach nor to usurp authority over the man. ...  For Adam was first formed, then Eve.&#148;  1 Corinthians xi. 8,9:  &#147;For the man is not of the women, but the woman of the man.  Neither was the man created for the woman but the woman for the man.&#148; </p>
			<p>
			In all the great cathedrals in England and in some here in New York, boys from ten to fifteen chant the hymns of praise that woman&apos;s lips may not profane, while they, oblivious to those insults to their sex, swell the listening crowd, and worship the very God who they are told made them slaves, and cursed them with sufferings that time can never mitigate. </p>
			<p>
			When in England, I visited the birthplace of Dean Stanley.  The old homestead was occupied by a curate and his two daughters. 
			<pb n="18" facs="8346022.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346022">022</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>18</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>
			They escorted us all over the place&#151;in the school where poor children were taught, in the old church where the dean had long preached.  &#147;Do you see that table cover in the altar?&#148;  said one of the daughters.  &#147;Sister and I worked that.&#148;  &#147;Did you spread it on the table?&#148;  said I.  &#147;Oh, no,&#148; said she; &#147;no woman is allowed to enter this enclosure.&#148;  &#147;Why?&#148; said I.  &#147;Oh!  it is too sacred.&#148;  &#147;But,&#148; said I, &#147;men go there; and it is said that women are purer, more delicate, refined, and naturally religious than they are.&#148;  &#147;Yes, but women are not allowed.&#148;  &#147;Shall I explain the reason to you?&#148;  I replied.  &#147;Yes,&#148; she said, with a look of surprise.  &#147;Well,&#148; said I, &#147;it is because the Church believes that woman brought sin into the world, that she was the cause of man&apos;s fall from holiness, that she was cursed of God, and has ever since been in collusion with the devil.  Hence, the Church has considered her unfit to sing in the choir or enter the Holy of Holies.&#148;  She looked very thoughtful, and said, &#147;I never supposed these old customs had such significance.&#148; &#147;Yes,&#148; I replied, &#147;every old custom, every fashion, every point of etiquette, is based on some principle, and women ignorantly submit to many degrading customs, because they do not understand their origin.&#148; </p>
			<p>
			These indignities have their root in the doctrine of original sin, gradually developed in the canon law&#151;a doctrine never taught in the primitive Christian Church.  In spite of the life, character and teachings of Jesus, ever proclaiming the essential equality and oneness of the whole human family, the priesthood, claiming apostolic descent, so interprets Christianity as to make it the basis of all religious and political disqualifications for women, sustaining the rights of man alone. </p>
			<p>
			The offices women held during the apostolic age she has been gradually deprived of through ecclesiastical enactments.  Although, during the first four hundred years of the Christian Church, women were the chosen companions of Jesus and his followers, doing their utmost to spread the new faith, as preachers, elders, deacons,p officiating in all the sacraments, yet these facts are carefully excluded from all the English translations of the Scriptures; while woman&apos;s depravity, inferiority and subordination are dwelt upon wherever the text will admit of it.  Under all the changes in advancing civilization for the last fifteen hundred years, this one idea of woman has been steadily promulgated; and to-day, in the full blaze of the sunlight of the late years of the nineteenth century, it is echoed in the pulpit by nearly every sect and in the halls of legislation by political leaders. </p>
			<p>
			Whatever oppressions man has suffered, they have invariably fallen more heavily on woman.  Whatever new liberties advancing civilization has brought to man, ever the smallest measure has been accorded to woman, as a result of church teaching.  The effect of this is seen in every department of life. </p>
			<p>
			There is nothing so cheap as womanhood in the commerce of the world.  You can scarcely take up a paper that does not herald some 
			<pb n="19" facs="8346023.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346023">023</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>19</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>outrage on woman, from the dignified matron on her way to church to the girl of fourteen gathering wild flowers on her way to school.  I hold men in high places responsible for the actions of the lower orders.  The sentiments and opinions expressed by clergymen and legislators mould the morals of the highway.  So long as the Church and the State, in their creeds and codes, make woman an outcast, she will be the sport of the multitude.  Whatever can be done to dignify her in the eyes of man will be a shield and helmet for her protection.  If the same respect the masses are educated to feel for cathedrals, altars, symbols and sacraments was ex tended to the mothers of the race, as it should be, all these distracting problems, in which their interest are involved, would be speedily settled.  You cannot go so low down in the scale of being as to find them who would enter our churches to desecrate the altars or toss about the emblem of the sacrament, because they have been educated with a holy reverence for these things.  But where are any lessons of reverence for woman taught to the multitude? </p>
			<p>
			And yet is she not, as the mother of the race, more exalted than sacraments, symbols, altars, and vast cathedral domes?  Are not the eternal principles of justice engraven on her heart more sacred than canons, creeds and codes written on parchment by Jesuits, bishops, cardinals and popes?  Yet where shall we look for lessons of honor and respect to her? </p>
			<p>
			Do our sons in the law schools rise from their studies of the invidious statutes and opinions of jurists in regard to women with a higher respect for their mothers?  By no means.  Every line of the old common law of England on which the American system of jurisprudence is based, touching the interest of women, is, in a measure, responsible for the wrongs she suffers to-day. </p>
			<p>
			Do our sons in their theological seminaries rise from their studies of the Bible, and the popular commentaries on the passages of Scripture concerning woman&apos;s creation and position in the scale of being, with an added respect for their mothers?  By no means.  They come ofttimes fresh from the perusal of what they suppose to be God&apos;s will and law, fresh from communion with the unseen, perhaps with the dew of inspiration on their lips, to preach anew the subjection of one-half the race to the other </p>
			<p>
			A very striking fact, showing the outrages women patiently endure through the perversion of their religious sentiments by crafty priests, is seen in the treatment of the Hindu widow, the civil law in her case, as in so many others, being practically annulled by theological dogmas. </p>
			<p>
			&#147;The most liberal of the Hindu schools of jurisprudence,&#148; 
			<anchor xml:id="n023-01">
			
			</anchor>
			 says Maine, &#147;that prevailing in Bengal proper, gives a childless widow the enjoyment of her husband&apos;s property under certain restrictive conditions during her life;&#148; and in this it agrees with many bodies of unwritten local custom.  If there are male children, they succeed at once; but if there are none the widow comes in for her life before 
			<note n="n023-01" place="bottom">
			* Early History of Institutions, Lecture XI, on the Property of Married Women. </note>
			<pb n="20" facs="8346024.bmp">
			<!--<pageinfo>
			<controlpgno entity="n8346024">024</controlpgno>
			<printpgno>20</printpgno></pageinfo>-->
			</pb>the collateral relatives.  At the present moment, marriages among the upper classes of Hindus being very commonly infertile, a considerable portion of the soil of the wealthiest Indian provinces is in the hands of childless widows as tenants for life.  But it was exactly in Bengal proper that the English, on entering India, found the suttee, or widow-burning, not merely an occasional, but a constant and almost universal practice with the wealthier classes; and, as a rule, it was only the childless widow, and never the widow with minor children, who burnt herself on her husband&apos;s funeral pyre.  There is no question that there was the closest connection between the law and the religious custom; and the widow was made to sacrifice herself, in order that her tenancy for life might be gotten rid of.  The anxiety of her family that the rite should be performed, which seemed so striking to the first English observers of the practice, was in fact explained by the coarsest motives; but the Brahmins who exhorted her to the sacrifice were undoubtedly influenced by a purely professional dislike to her enjoyment of property.  The ancient rule of the civil law, which made her a tenant for life, could not be gotten rid of; but it was combated by the modern institution, which made it her duty to devote herself to a frightful death.  The reasoning on this subject, current even in comparatively ancient times, is thus given in the Mitakshava:  &#147;The wealth of a regenerate man is designed for religious uses; and a woman&apos;s succession to such property is unfit, because she is not competent to the performance of religious rites.&#148;  Thus the liberal provisions of the civil law were disposed of by burning the widow, and she was made willing for the sacrifice by a cultivated sense of religious duty.  What is true in this case is true of women in all ages.  They have been trained by their religion to sacrifice themselves, body and soul, for the men of their families and to build up the churches.  We do not burn the bodies of women to-day; but we humiliate them in a thousands ways, and chiefly by our theologies.  So long as the pulpits teach woman&apos;s inferiority and subjection, she can never command that honor and respect of the ignorant classes needed for her safety and protection.  There is nothing more pathetic in all history than the hopeless resignation of woman to the outrages she has been taught to believe are ordained of God. </p>
	</div>
	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
 